Guide to the Adella Liebenow Wotherspoon Photographs and Papers 1860-2004 PR 400
New-York Historical Society
Adella Liebenow Wotherspoon photographs and papers
1860-2004
New-York Historical Society
Wotherspoon, Adella Martha Liebenow, 1903-2004
PR 400
approximately 4 Linear feet in 2 document boxes, 3 flat boxes, and 1 oversize folder.
Photographs, postcards, sacramental certificates, passports, naturalization papers, scrapbooks, and ephemera documenting the lives of members of the German-American Liebenow, Weber, and Wulf families, at least six of whom died during the burning of the paddle steamer General Slocum on June 15, 1904. The Slocum disaster, on New York's East River, claimed an estimated 1,021 of the 1,342 passengers on board, many of whom were women and children who could not swim. Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon (1903–2004), donor of the collection, was the youngest survivor. She unveiled a memorial to the unknown dead in 1905, and lived to be the sole survivor of what was, until the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001, the single greatest loss of life in New York City history.
Arrangement
The Adella Liebenow Wotherspoon Photographs and Papers are organized in three series:
Series I.
Family photographs and documents, 1860-2004
Series II.
​General Slocum disaster scrapbooks, 1904-1908, 1934
Series III.
​General Slocum disaster memorial programs, newspaper clippings, ephemera, 1904-2004
Series I is sorted alphabetically by surname. Series II and III are sorted chronologically.
Biographical / Historical Note
Adella Martha (Liebenow) Wotherspoon (1903–2004), sometimes known by the nicknames "Dolly" and "Tiby," was the youngest daughter of Paul and Anna (Wulf) Liebenow, both New York City natives and the children of German immigrants. Paul (1871–1910), the son of Heinrich and Henriette (Pisch) Liebenow, married Anna (1872–1947), the daughter of Heinrich and Helene (Brauer) Wulf, in 1896. Their first daughter, Helen, was born in 1898. She was followed by Anna in 1901, and Adella, who was born November 28, 1903. Adella, at the age of six months, became the youngest survivor of the General Slocum steamboat disaster of June 15, 1904.
The General Slocum, a popular paddle steamer chartered for the 17th annual Sunday school excursion of St. Mark's Evangelical Lutheran Church, was destined for Locust Grove, a picnic site on the north shore of Long Island. The ship rode up the East River carrying just over 1,300 passengers, many of them young mothers with their children from the vicinity of St. Mark's, the Manhattan neighborhood known then as Kleindeutschland (Little Germany) and today a part of the East Village. For most of those passengers it was to be their first—and last—trip by pleasure boat.
On board that morning was the Liebenow family—Paul, Anna, and daughters Helen, Anna, and Adella. They joined Paul's sisters, Martha Liebenow (1875–1904), Annie (Liebenow) Weber (1873–1905), and Annie's husband, Frank Weber (1869–1936), with their two children, Emma (1893–1904), and Frank Weber Jr. (1898–1904). Also with them was "Aunt" Katie King (circa 1878–1904), the Irish-born fiancée of Anna (Wulf) Liebenow's brother, Henry Wulf (1876–1912). It is unclear if Henry Wulf was part of the group, but he and Katie were due to be married on September 15, 1904, so Katie was practically part of the family.
Through a cause that will never be known, the Slocum caught fire almost immediately after embarking at 9:40 a.m. Smoke billowing from a lower deck was at first attributed to "chowder cooking" by the jolly excursionists. Twenty-six minutes later the ship exploded in flames off Randall's Island. Life vests crumbled to dust in the hands of panicked passengers. Lifeboats were found wired in place. Shoddy canvas fire hoses burst under water pressure. At 10:10 the Slocum beached on North Brother Island, off the Bronx. A staggering 1,021 people died, if not by burning, then by drowning. Until the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001, the General Slocum disaster was the single greatest loss of life in New York City history.
The eleven-member Liebenow-Weber party was reduced by six. Nearly all suffered scorching. Frank and Annie (Liebenow) Weber survived, although Annie's hair caught fire. Paul Liebenow stayed on the ship looking for his children until his clothing began to burn away. His wife, Anna, was severely burned down her side as she clung to the ship with one arm while shielding the infant Adella in the other, dropping into the water only when she could no longer bear the pain. She and the baby were eventually reunited with Paul, Annie, and Frank. Dead were Martha Liebenow and Katie King, Emma and Frank Weber Jr., and Helen and Anna Liebenow. (As Adella later phrased it, she lost two aunts, two cousins, and two sisters to the Slocum.) While little Anna Liebenow's body was recovered (her parents carefully preserving the shoes she wore that day), Helen's was never identified. She is believed to lie in the communal grave of the unknown dead of the General Slocum at Lutheran Cemetery (now called All Faiths Cemetery) in Middle Village, Queens. On the first anniversary of the tragedy 18-month-old Adella pulled a cord to unveil a monument to their memory.
Like other survivors, Paul Liebenow spent his subsequent days in dazed shock, but with one difference: he gathered in scrapbooks every memento and newspaper article he could find about the fire (in German and in English), every piece of ephemera and correspondence, even including the receipt for the new suit and hat he'd purchased specifically for the St. Mark's excursion. Adella said the compilation of his scrapbooks was a form of therapy. Paul never truly recovered, and died in 1910. His sister, Annie Weber, died a week shy of the first anniversary of the disaster, on June 9, 1905, as noted on the back of her photograph, "from effects of [the] Slocum."
Soon after Paul's death Anna (Wulf) Liebenow and Adella moved to Watchung, New Jersey, where Adella, who became a high school teacher, married James Wotherspoon (1903–1982) in 1930. Anna died in 1947, and for many years after Adella avoided the annual commemorations at Lutheran Cemetery and Tompkins Square Park in Manhattan, where another memorial to the Slocum dead had been dedicated in 1906. The rediscovery of her father's scrapbooks, stored in the attic along with photographs and family papers, renewed Adella's interest and involvement in the Organization of the General Slocum Survivors. She began attending events again when she was 85, and made it to most of them until shortly before her death at the age of 100 on January 26, 2004. Usually she brought along her sister Anna's shoes, and the dress she herself had worn to unveil the monument to the unknown dead at Lutheran Cemetery on June 15, 1905.
With the death of Catherine Connelly in 2002, who, at the remarkable age of 109 was the oldest survivor of the General Slocum, Adella, once the youngest survivor of that fateful day, became its oldest and sole survivor. Sadly, she missed the Slocum centennial by just shy of five months. On her death she bequeathed her scrapbooks, photographs, dress, and sister's shoes to the New-York Historical Society, where they were exhibited in The General Slocum and Little Germany, June 15 – August 22, 2004.
The fullest account of the disaster is Edward T. O'Donnell's Ship Ablaze: The Tragedy of the Steamboat General Slocum (New York: Broadway Books, 2003), available at the New-York Historical Society under call number F128 VK1257.G4 O29 2003.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Adella Liebenow Wotherspoon, 2004.
Related Material at the New-York Historical Society
In addition to the many books and other publications documenting the General Slocum disaster, which may be found through BobCat, the library's online catalog, the New-York Historical Society holds the following archival material stemming from the event and its aftermath. (Click the hyperlinks for details.)
• General Slocum (Steamboat) dollar bill and letter, [1904]. Call phrase: AHMC - General Slocum (Steamboat).
• Minnie Weiss letter to Emma Bruning, 1904 July 15. Call phrase: AHMC - Weiss, Minnie.
• Organization of the General Slocum Survivors. Minutes, 1951-1963. Call phrase: BV Organization.
• Edwin Robinson letter, 1954 November 19. Call phrase: AHMC - Robinson, Edwin.
• George E. Stonebridge photograph collection [graphic]. Call phrase: PR-066, Box 64, 65, 70. Available online.
• New-York Historical Society Collection of Geographic Images. Call phrase: PR-020, Subseries IA: MANHATTAN - BOXED MATERIAL, Box 100, Folders 10-11: Events-Shipwrecks-General Slocum Shipwreck and sinking, 1904. Finding aid.
• Samuel H. Berg. [Scrapbook of clippings relating to the General Slocum disasters] (1909?). Call number: F128 VK1257.G4 B4.
• Scrapbook of newspaper clippings relating to the General Slocum Steamboat disaster, 1904. Call number: F128 VK1257.G4 S4 Oversize.
• [Newspaper clippings pertaining to the General Slocum steamboat disaster of 1904 and the subsequent investigations]: scrapbook, 1904-1908. Call number: F128 VK1257.G4 S42 1904 Oversize.
Scope and Contents
The Adella Liebenow Wotherspoon Photographs and Papers document the extended Liebenow, Weber, and Wulf families of New York City, German immigrants and their American-born offspring, whose lives centered on the community known as Kleindeutschland (Little Germany), in Manhattan's East Village, and other German enclaves. The collection contains sacramental certificates marking baptisms, confirmations, and marriages, most of them written in German even when the events took place in New York, which speaks to the pervasiveness of German language and culture throughout their lives. Also present are German passports issued to Adella's paternal grandmother, Henriette (Pisch) Liebenow (1846–1881) in 1860, and her maternal grandfather, Heinrich Wulf (circa 1842–1909) in 1865. Both of Adella's grandfathers, Henrich Wulf and Heinrich Liebenow (1839–1902), became United States citizens, as indicated by their naturalization papers of 1872 and 1890.
At the heart of the collection are the late 19th- and early 20th-century cabinet card photographs of family members, six of whom died in the General Slocum tragedy of June 15, 1904: Adella's sisters, Helen (1898–1904) and Anna (1901–1904) Liebenow; her cousins, Emma (1893–1904) and Frank Weber Jr. (1898–1904); and aunts, Martha Liebenow (1875–1904) and Katie King (circa 1878–1904). [Although her photograph is identified as "Aunt Katie King," Katie was not technically a relative; she was the fiancée of Adella's uncle, Henry Wulf (1876–1912), whom she planned to marry on September 15, 1904.]
The collection's two scrapbooks include additional photographs and even artifacts (such as a hatpin Paul Liebenow retrieved from an unknown victim's body on North Brother Island), but are full, mainly, of German and English-language newspaper coverage of the Slocum disaster, rescue efforts, memorial ceremonies, and the subsequent hearings and trials.
And rounding out the collection is a small group of newspaper clippings, ceremonial programs, postcards, and interviews confirming Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon's role as the youngest and, ultimately, sole survivor of the General Slocum.
Ephemera.; Naturalization records.; Passports.; Photographs.; Postcards.; Press clippings.; Programs (documents); Scrapbooks.; Fires -- New York (State) -- New York.; German Americans -- New York (State) -- New York.; Steamboat disasters -- New York (State) -- New York; General Slocum (Steamboat); Organization of the General Slocum Survivors; Liebenow (Family); Weber (Family); Wulf family
- Series I. Family photographs and documents, 1860-2004
  Arrangement
  Sorted alphabetically by surname, with photographs preceding documents. Names in bold, underlined type indicate those killed in the General Slocum disaster of June 15, 1904.
  - King, Catherine "Katie" (circa 1878-1904)
    - Catherine "Katie" King. Photograph, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Cabinet card portrait of Catherine "Katie" King by Bloomingdale Bros., 59th St. & 3rd Ave., N.Y. Identified (verso) as "Aunt Katie King (Uncle Henry['s] Katie) / Died on the Scolum [sic] / June 15, 1904 / Were going to be married / Sept 15, 1904."
      A notation (verso) by N-YHS staff reads: "b. 1888 [sic] in Ireland lived 311 E 37th St / fiancée of Henry Liebenow." Henry Liebenow died in 1900, so Katie King was more likely engaged to marry Henry Wulf (1876-1912), brother of Anna (Wulf) Liebenow. According to her death certificate, Catherine King was 26 when she died on June 15, 1904. That places her birth circa 1878.
  - Liebenow, Anna (1901-1904)
    - Anna Liebenow. Photograph (christening), [1901 February 20] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
      Cabinet card portrait of Anna Liebenow in her christening gown. Identified (verso) as "Anna / 3 month old / 3 year old / time of Scolum [sic]." (According to her baptism certificate in Box 2, Folder 1, Anna was christened on February 20, 1901.) A duplicate of this photograph is framed with images of Anna's sisters in Box 1, Folder 3.
    - Anna, "Dolly," and Helen Liebenow. Photographs (christening), [1898, 1901, 1904] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
      A single frame holding three cabinet card portraits of the daughters of Paul and Anna (Wulf) Liebenow in their christening gowns, identified (verso) as:
      [left] "Anna Christina Liebenow / Born Jan 1st / 1901." Unidentifed photographer.
      [center] "Adella Martha Liebenow / Born Nov. 28, 1903." Frank Wuttge, Photographic Art Studio, 920 Third Avenue, New York.
      [right] "Helen Henrietta Liebenow / Born August 18, 1898." Continental Photo Gallery, 794 Third Avenue, Bet. 48th & 49th Sts., New York.
      The photograph of Anna is identical to the one in Box 1, Folder 2. The photograph of Helen is the same as the one identified as sister Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon in Box 1, Folder 19.
    - Anna Liebenow. Baptism certificate [in German], 1901 February 20 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
      Baptism certificate for Anna Christine Liebenow. Ceremony performed by Dr. Edward F. Moldehnke, Pastor of St. Peter's Lutheran Church, New York.
  - Liebenow, Anna (Wulf) (1872-1947)
    - Anna (Wulf) Liebenow. Photograph (2 copies), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
      Cabinet card portrait (right-facing profile) of Anna (Wulf) Liebenow by A. Kyle, 1316 Third Ave., N.Y. Identified (verso) as "Mama."
    - Anna (Wulf) Liebenow. Photograph, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
      Cabinet card portrait (left-facing profile) of Anna (Wulf) Liebenow by A. Kyle, 1316 Third Ave., N.Y., Bet. 75th and 76th Streets. Identified (verso) as "Mama."
    - Anna (Wulf) Liebenow. Confirmation certificate [in German], 1889 April 14 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
      Confirmation certificate of Anna Christiane Wulf. Ceremony performed by Dr. Edward F. Moldehnke, Pastor of St. Peter's Lutheran Church, New York.
    - Anna (Wulf) Liebenow. Birthday card, 1904 [January 26] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
      Birthday card to "Aunt Annie" from Emma and Frank Weber, dated, simply, 1904. Anna (Wulf) Liebenow was born in New York on January 26, 1872.
  - Liebenow, Heinrich / Henry (1839-1902)
    - Heinrich / Henry Liebenow. Photograph + copy print (2 folders), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6-7)
      Cabinet card portrait, with copy print, of Heinrich / Henry Liebenow by W. Fricke, Photographer, 50 Bowery, Above Atlantic Garden, New York. Identified (recto and verso) as "Grandpa Liebenow."
    - Heinrich / Henry Liebenow. Marriage certificate [in German], 1867 May 19 (Oversize FF, Item 3)
      Marriage certificate for Heinrich Liebenow and Henriette Pisch, issued at New York City.
    - Heinrich / Henry Liebenow. U.S. Certificate of naturalization, 1890 October 16 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
      Issued by the Superior Court of the City of New York.
    - Heinrich / Henry Liebenow. Funeral remembrance card [in German], [1902 March 5] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Liebenow, Helen (1898-1904)
    - Helen Liebenow. Photograph, circa 1899 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
      Cabinet card portrait of Helen Liebenow as an infant in her carriage. Identified (verso) as "Sister Helen / 1 year old / 6 years in Aug / died on Scolum [sic]." Another copy of this photograph appears in the scrapbook in Box 4.
    - Helen Liebenow. Photograph, circa 1899 (Offsite-box 4, Volume smaller scrapbook)
      Cabinet card portrait of Helen Liebenow as an infant in her carriage. Identified (on scrapbook page) as "Our Helen." Identical to the photograph in Box 1, Folder 8.
    - Helen Liebenow. Photograph, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
      Cabinet card photograph of two small girls on a doorstep, both holding brooms. The taller girl is identified (recto) as "Helen." An N-YHS staff notation (verso) suggests the other child is possibly Anna Liebenow.
    - Helen Liebenow. Baptism certificate [in German], 1898 September 4 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
      Baptism certificate for "Helene Henriette" Liebenow. Ceremony performed by Dr. A. B. Moldenke.
  - Liebenow, Henriette (Pisch) (1846-1881)
    - Henriette (Pisch) Liebenow. Photograph, undated (Offsite-box 4, Volume smaller scrapbook)
      Carte-de-visite portrait of Henriette (Pisch) Liebenow identified (on scrapbook page) as "Grama Liebenow."
    - Henriette (Pisch) Liebenow. "Reise Pass" (passport) [in German], 1860 (Oversize FF, Item 4)
      Issued to "Henriette Lisette Alvine Pisch" at Bergen, Germany.
  - Liebenow, Henry (circa 1868-1900)
    - Henry Liebenow. Photograph + copy print (2 folders), 1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10-11)
      Cabinet card portrait, with copy print, of Henry Liebenow, by H. Schoerry, 43 Ave. A., N.Y. Identified (verso) as "Uncle Henry Liebenow."
  - Liebenow, Martha (1875-1904)
    - Martha Liebenow. Photograph, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
      Cabinet card portrait of Martha Liebenow by Winslow, 274 Grand Street, New York. Identified (verso) as "Aunt Martha Liebenow / Died on the Scolum [sic] / June 15, 1904 / 29 years old."
  - Liebenow, Paul (1871-1910)
    - Paul Liebenow. Photograph + copy print (2 folders), 1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13-14)
      Cabinet card portrait, with copy print, of Paul Liebenow by H. Schoerry, 43 Ave. A., N.Y. Cabinet card identified (recto & verso) as "Papa." Copy print identified as "Papa Liebenow."
    - Paul Liebenow. Marriage certificate [in German], 1896 October 12 (Oversize FF, Item 5)
      Certificate recording the marriage of Paul Liebenow and Anna Christiane Wulf on September 15, 1896, by Dr. Edward F. Moldehnke, Pastor of St. Peter's Lutheran Church, New York.
    - Paul Liebenow. Certificate of sympathy, 1910 February 2 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
      Organization of Gen'l Slocum Survivors, certificate of sympathy issued to Anna C. (Wulf) Liebenow on the death of her husband, Paul Liebenow.
    - Paul Liebenow, et al. Lutheran Cemetery deed, receipts, interment list, 1897-1990 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Weber, Anna "Annie" (Liebenow) (1873-1905)
    - Anna "Annie" (Liebenow) Weber. Photograph, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
      Cabinet card portrait of Anna "Annie" (Liebenow) Weber by Jacks Studio, 136 Bowery, N.Y. Identified (verso) as "Aunt Annie / Liebenow Weber / Died June 9, 1905 / was on the Scolum [sic] / Died June / 1905 / from effects of / Scolum [sic]."
      For Annie Weber's personal account of the General Slocum disaster, see John Wesley Hanson, New York's Awful Excursion Boat Horror (1904), 193-196, available online and at the New-York Historical Society under call number F128 VK1257.G4 H3.
  - Weber, Emma (1893-1904)
    - Emma Weber. Photograph, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
      Cabinet card portrait of Emma Weber by I. [or J.] Klein, 61 Ave. A, New York. Identified (verso) as "Cousin Emma Weber / Died on Scolum [sic] June 15, 1904 / 10 years old."
  - Weber, Frank Charles (1869-1936)
    - Frank Charles Weber. Photograph, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
      Cabinet card portrait of Frank Charles Weber by Frank Wuttge, Successor to Bach, 27 Ave. A, New York. Identified (verso) as "Uncle Frank Weber / was on the Scolum [sic] saved / badly bunt [burnt]."
  - Weber, Frank Jr. (1898-1904)
    - Frank Weber Jr.. Photograph, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
      Cabinet card portrait of Frank Weber Jr. by Henry D. Schoerry, 43 Avenue A, New York. Identified (verso) as "June 15, 1904 / Frank Weber / Died on the Scolum [sic] / 7 year old cousin."
    - Frank Weber Jr.. Photograph, undated (Offsite-box 4, Volume smaller scrapbook)
      Cabinet card portrait of Frank Weber Jr., wearing 18th-century court costume and wig, by I. [or J.] Klein, Photographer, 61 Avenue A, New York. Identified (on scrapbook page) as "Cousin Frank."
  - Wotherspoon, Adella (Liebenow) (1903-2004)
    - Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Photograph (christening), [1904] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
      Cabinet card portrait of Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon in her christening gown by Continental Photo Gallery, 794 Third Avenue, Bet. 48th & 49th Sts., New York. Identified (verso) as "Dolly / 3 months old." This image is identical to the one identified as sister Helen Liebenow (1898-1904) in Box 1, Folder 3.
    - Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Photograph, 1905 June 15 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
      Framed studio portrait of Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon by Schaidner, 183 E. 124, N.Y. Identified (verso) as "Adella Liebenow / Dolly / 18 months old / unveiling Scolum [sic] Monument / June 15, 1905." [New-York Historical Society negative no. 86693d.]
    - Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Photograph, 1905 June 15 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
      Studio portrait of Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon by Schaidner, 183 E. 124, N.Y. Identified (verso) as "Adella Liebenow / 18 months old time of unvailing [sic] / June 15, 1905."
    - Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Photograph, circa 1909 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
      Cabinet card portrait of Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Identified (verso) as "5 years old / Dolly / 65 E 122 Street / NY."
    - Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Photograph (graduation), 1917 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
      Studio portrait of Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon by H. Mallison, 180 E. 82nd St., N.Y. Identified (inside protective cover) as "13 years old 1917 / Dolly." Adella is holding a rolled scroll so this photograph likely commemorates her graduation from grammar school or junior high school.
    - Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Photograph (wedding party), [1930 June 28] (Oversize FF, Item 1)
      Proof portrait of the wedding party of James and Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon by Underwood & Underwood. The couple married at Watchung, New Jersey, June 28, 1930.
    - Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Photographs (birthday collage), 1998 November 28 (Oversize FF, Item 2)
      Collage of General Slocum disaster images, dedicated "To Adella on her 95th birthday" from Kathy Jolowicz, Zion-St. Mark's Church Historian.
    - Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Photographs (color prints), 1998, 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
      Eight color photographs of Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon attending General Slocum memorial events in Tompkins Square Park, Manhattan, All Faiths (formerly Lutheran) Cemetery, Middle Village, Queens, and Trinity Lutheran Church, also in Middle Village.
    - Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Birth certificate, [1903 November 28] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
      Certified copy, issued by the Bureau of Records and Statistics, Department of Health, The City of New York, November 9, 1962.
    - Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Personal copy of Wild Flowers from Whittier (New York: Cupples & Leon Company, 1909), [1912 December 25] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)